<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A just reproof to Mr. Richard Baxter, for his pride and insolence, in calumniating that great, and most orthodox council of Ephesus, &amp;c.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46387</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12730367</idno>
  <idno type="VID">66452</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240951230</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing J1238</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19081</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12730367</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46387)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66452)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 694:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A just reproof to Mr. Richard Baxter, for his pride and insolence, in calumniating that great, and most orthodox council of Ephesus, &amp;c.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to various arguments in Baxter's The Nonconformists plea for peace.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Baxter, Richard, 1615-1691. --  Nonconformists plea for peace.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66452:1"/>
            <p>A JUST REPROOF TO Mr. Richard Baxter, FOR HIS PRIDE AND INSOLENCE, In Calumniating that Great, and Most Orthodox Council OF EPHESUS, &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Rom. 12. 3.</bibl>
               <p>I say through the Grace given unto me, to every Man that is among you, not to think of himself more Highly than he ought to Think, but to Think Soberly, according as God hath dealt to every Man the Measure of Faith.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1680.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="censure">
            <pb facs="tcp:66452:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66452:2"/>
            <head>TO M<seg rend="sup">R.</seg> RICHARD BAXTER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF there be any such Vice, as PRIDE, certainly that man must needs be guilty of it, who <hi>Undervalues</hi> the <hi>Gifts,</hi> or <hi>Grace</hi> of any one, whosoever he be, especially of such a one, who deserves more to be <hi>Honor'd</hi> then himself: How then can you escape the Censure of being <hi>a very Proud Man,</hi> who Slight and Disesteem the Assembly of so many <hi>Venerable</hi> Persons, and in a particular manner undertake to <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preciate</hi> the most Learned, and Pious Endeavors, and Performances of that <hi>Admirable Man,</hi> Saint CYRIL? By the <hi>Zealous</hi> Regard I have to the <hi>Right Notion</hi> of the Two <hi>Natures,</hi> and ONE <hi>Person</hi> of our Blessed REDEEMER, and a deep Sense of the constant Endeavors of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> and of <hi>Men Puft up</hi> by their Unsanctified <hi>Knowledge,</hi> to <hi>Pervert</hi> our Thoughts concerning HIM. I am mov'd to <hi>Indignation</hi> against you for your most Wicked Attempt to bring an <hi>Odium</hi> upon the Memory of that most Reverend Bishop, who so Learnedly, so Piously, so Effectually La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor'd to deliver the Church of Christ from the <hi>Pestilent</hi> Heresie of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storius.</hi> That you may further perceive why I apprehend My self in a special manner concern'd to Oppose you, I shall here Recite a Passage in a small Treatise, I lately Publisht against another Enemy of the Church of <hi>England, viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>John Serjeant, Regula Fidei — FIDEI formata Cogitat. Ulteriora de Natura Fidei Verè Christia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> p. 26.</p>
            <p>That what I have here Deliver'd, and that every Doctrine I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Preacht,</hi> or <hi>Printed</hi> (having been now a <hi>Minister of the Gospel about</hi> Twenty years) is <hi>True,</hi> I am ready to Testifie with my Blood: I Appeal to your own Conscience whether you would Do the like in Defence of All the Doctrines, or Propositions you have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor'd to <hi>Impose</hi> upon the World, even in your Printed Books: If not, Consider how <hi>Vain,</hi> and <hi>Trifling</hi> a person you have shown your self to be in <hi>Publishing your own Particular</hi> Conceits, and loose <hi>Variable</hi> Opinions (as <hi>Rules,</hi> and <hi>Maxims)</hi> in Matters of <hi>Universal,</hi> and <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal</hi> Concernment. Certainly it was your most sinful SELF-CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CEITEDNESS that prompted you to such an Endeavor to <hi>Defame</hi> not only the <hi>Council of Ephesus</hi> and Saint <hi>Cyril,</hi> but also the Three other most Celebratel <hi>General Councils.</hi> I will not say your <hi>Humor</hi> now inclines you to Think favorably of the <hi>Arrians</hi> (though they surely are since of the <hi>NONCONFORMISTS to the Church of England)</hi> but this I shall say, that by my <hi>Zeal</hi> against <hi>Arrianism,</hi> and my most <hi>Ardent</hi> Affection to the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of those <hi>Holy Bishops,</hi> who so earnestly endeavor'd at the Council of <hi>Nice</hi> to Cut it off, Root, and Branch. I am induc'd to an <hi>Abhorrency</hi> of those words of yours, <hi>p.</hi> 267th of your Book entitled. <hi>The Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formists Plea for Peace. Their Famous General Councils, which we justly honor for that which they did well, were shamefully Militant: Even the</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:66452:3"/>
               <hi>first and most honored Council at</hi> Nice, <hi>was with great difficulty kept in Peace by the Personal presence, Wisedom, and Authority of</hi> Constantine, <hi>Preaching peace to the Preachers of peace, Burning their Libels of mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual accusation, and silencing their contentious wranglings, and constrein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to accord.</hi> Nazianzens <hi>descriptions of the Ignorance, and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solence,</hi> &amp;c. Though <hi>Constantine</hi> shew'd his Royal Prudence in own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Libells of mutual accusation (as you speak) it does not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low from hence that there was any thing either False, or written up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Principle of <hi>Envy,</hi> and <hi>Malice,</hi> in those Papers that were offer'd him by the <hi>Orthodox Bishops.</hi> 'Tis true, they were <hi>Militant</hi> indeed: but we defy your words in that you say they were shamefully Militant: The <hi>Spirit of Glory rested on them:</hi> They Fought indeed, but they Fought <hi>the Good Fight of</hi> FAITH, <hi>And laid hold on Eternal Life.</hi> You, it seems, are one of Many, who still Fight against their <hi>Ashes;</hi> but, Consider that you <hi>shall give account to Him, that is ready to Judge the Quick, and the Dead.</hi> I pray, Sir, Remember that <hi>Nazianzen</hi> (as you call him) was a Great <hi>Bishop:</hi> And certainly the Eminency of His Virtues tends much more to the Honor of <hi>Episcopacy,</hi> then the Faults of the Bishops he speaks against could ever do to its Disreputation. It can hardly be imagin'd how there could have been such Lasting, and Glorious Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of His True Learning, and Godliness, if He had never enjoy'd that <hi>Episcopal Grandeur,</hi> against which you have so great a Spight. The Glory of His Virtues shall shine to <hi>Illuminate</hi> the World throughout All Generations; whereas the Faults of the Bishops He speaks against can do little, or no Hurt now, unless by your, or some other mans <hi>Narrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of them to Ignorant People they shall again become <hi>Scandalous.</hi> And now, Sir, I shall mind you of those <hi>Strange</hi> words, p. 271. Nestorius <hi>a man of study, retirement, a poor garbe, a strict life, abhorring publick con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and loving quietness, but of a peevish Zeal against dissenters called Hereticks, as Enemies to the Churches unity, and peace; so that he present<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly persecuted many of them, even the</hi> Novatians <hi>themselves, and stirred up the Emperor to root them all out, and by Gods just Judgment received such measure, as he had measured.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such measure, as he had measur'd, which you Contemn as proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from a <hi>Peevish Zeal,</hi> a <hi>Persecuting</hi> Spirit <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And by a plain and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Consequence you Condemn that Great, and most Orthodox <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil</hi> of EPHESUS, so highly <hi>Venerated</hi> so many Hundred Years, by All the most Profoundly Learned and most Sincerely Pious <hi>Divines (Bishops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters)</hi> throughout the Whole Christian World. I must confess you are so Favorable as not to Condemn them, as adhering to any Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, but only for want of <hi>Logick,</hi> of your <hi>Nice Faculty</hi> of making Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctions <hi>&amp;c. I think, say you,</hi> p. 273. <hi>You will see that the Error of</hi> Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storius <hi>lay in his want of skill in speaking, and that one side spoke of a phrase</hi> de abstracto, <hi>and the other of the</hi> Concrete; <hi>and if so, both meant the same thing, though</hi> Cyril <hi>was judged to use the most skilful words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Could none of the <hi>Council</hi> find out this, that, S. <hi>Cyrils</hi> Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versie was a meer <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>? Don't you Pity these poor Ignorant men that they had not Read such <hi>Logick Books,</hi> as you have been vers'd in, that they might have attain'd to the Excellent Faculty of Distin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guishing between <hi>Abstract,</hi> and <hi>Concrete?</hi> Fie, Fie! Be Asham'd of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:66452:3"/> this <hi>Self-Conceit.</hi> Having said <hi>p.</hi> 275. Nestorius <hi>being thus contemn'd,</hi> Eutyches <hi>thought he would be Far enough from his Heresie, and said, that the Union of Christs Two Natures made them to be but One, you Assert in plain terms</hi> p. 288. <hi>that</hi> Cyril, Eutyches, <hi>and</hi> Dioscorus <hi>were all of one mind.</hi> Strange! that <hi>Eutyches</hi> being <hi>Startled</hi> at the Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Nestorius</hi> should <hi>Leap</hi> from his Heresie to the <hi>Contrary Extream,</hi> and yet nevertheless should Remain still in the same Mind with Him! <hi>who (say you of these Three) were all of One Mind?</hi> How would you <hi>Insult</hi> over Saint <hi>Cyril,</hi> if you could find him entangled in the like <hi>Self-contradiction?</hi> Having <hi>patcht up</hi> a great many <hi>Rags of History,</hi> you Reflect thus on the Stories you have told, the Particulars whereof I do not think it worth my pains to Examine: <hi>I have wrote this much to shew you how far the Patriarchal Seats conduced to the Churches Peace, and how far the Four First Councils of Bishops caused Christian Love, and Concord.</hi> Can those <hi>Bloody</hi> Animosities of persons most wilfully <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roncous</hi> against the <hi>Orthodox,</hi> upon supposition that they were Encreas'd by those most <hi>Solemn,</hi> and <hi>Authoritative</hi> Declarations of the Truth Concerning the PERSON of Our Saviour, by the Decrees of the <hi>Councils,</hi> Confirm'd by <hi>Princes,</hi> can, I say, those <hi>Bloody</hi> Animosities be justly Imputed to those Councils? 'Tis true, the End of their <hi>Determinations</hi> was not to Lessen the Animosities of those that will remain most willfully <hi>Erroneous</hi> against the <hi>Orthodox,</hi> for it was most Probable that they would be much heightned, and Enflam'd thereby; But it was this, that this Truth of the Greatest Importance might Shine more Clearly to All the World; so that All men, but such, who (as <hi>Job</hi> speaks) <hi>Rebell against the Light,</hi> may readily submit to the Power of it. How many Thousands in All Ages ever since those Councils sate have by their <hi>Determinations</hi> (as Instruments in the Hand of the GOD of Truth) been Confirm'd in the Christian Faith? I must Acknowledge my self to be in the Number of Them: And therefore I should violate the Peace of my Conscience, if I should not undertake the Vindication of those <hi>Councils</hi> against your subtle Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies, and Aspersions. That Self-conceit, which prompts you to slight the Labors of so many Holy Men, has entangled you in divers <hi>Erroneous</hi> Opinions which are great <hi>Impediments,</hi> if not <hi>wholly Obstru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive</hi> to True Piety. You say page 184. <hi>Not every Parishioner (yea in our experience not one of many) hath a full Trust in</hi> Gods Mercy, <hi>and a</hi> quiet Conscience, <hi>without both which they are not to come (to the Holy Communion.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I shall briefly Convince you of the Weakness of this Exception. By <hi>Full</hi> we are to understand nothing else, but <hi>Syncere,</hi> and <hi>Effcctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al viz.</hi> Such a Trust in <hi>Gods Mercy,</hi> as makes a man <hi>to Love God, because he first loved us,</hi> which <hi>Trust</hi> chiefly arises from a lively Sense of that most Comfortable Truth contain'd in these words, <hi>John</hi> 3. 16. <hi>For GOD so Loved the World, that he gave his Only Begotten Son that whosoever Believeth in Him should not Perish, but have Everlasting Life.</hi> The same Duties which are exprest by having a Full Trust in Gods Mercy are exprest in these words at the end of <hi>our Church Catechisme; to Repent them truly of their former Sins, stedfastly purposing to lead a new life, to have a lively Faith in Gods Mercy through Christ, with a</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:66452:4"/>
               <hi>Thankful Remembrance of his Death, and be in Charity with all men.</hi> Now is it possible but that he who Doth this should have a Quiet Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science? 'Tis true, if a man conceit that he is in the Number of the <hi>Godly</hi> only upon account of the great Dreads, and Terrors of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science that he has suffer'd, and of the great Anguish he feels, or has ever felt in his Soul, arising from the Apprehensions of the Horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Danger that his Sins, and wickedness have brought him into, and from a Sense of that <hi>Vexation of Spirit</hi> that is Imply'd in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of all Sin, But in the mean time does <hi>Habitually</hi> Love the World, Minds Earthly things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 'Tis no wonder if his Conscience be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet. But he that so Believes in the LORD <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> as to <hi>Set his Affection on things that are Above, not on things that are on the Earth, to Rejoyce in Tribulation, and Love his Enemies,</hi> sincerely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serving that Great Duty to Do to Every Man, as he would in the like Case that Any man should Do unto him, certainly he Feels the Power of those words of the Blessed Apostle. <hi>Colossians</hi> 3. 15. <hi>Let the Peace of God Rule in your hearts, to the which also ye are called in one Body, and be ye Thankful.</hi> Rom. 5. 1. 2. <hi>Therefore being Justi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed by Faith, we have Peace with God through our Lord Jesus Christ. By whom also we have access by Faith into this Grace, wherein we stand, and rejoyce in the Hope of the Glory of God.</hi> Galatians 5, 22. <hi>The Fruit of the Spirit is Love, Joy, Peace</hi> &amp;c. 2. Thessalonians 5. 16. <hi>Rejoyce Evermore.</hi> If you will ponder these words in your Heart, they will certainly incline you to apprehend that you have done great Disservice to the God <hi>of Love, and Peace, the Father of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and God of All Comfort,</hi> in slighting that Holy Admonition that they who come to the Holy Communion should come with a Full Trust. Page 194, You <hi>Talk thus: The</hi> Nonconformists <hi>that think that for the main there is nothing but good contain'd in most of the Prayers of the Liturgie: yet think that they are greatly</hi> disorder'd, <hi>and</hi> defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive; <hi>neither formed according to the order of</hi> matter, <hi>nor of the</hi> Lords Prayer, <hi>but like an immethodical Sermon which is unsuitable to the high Subjects, and honorable Work of Holy Worship.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you most <hi>Cunningly</hi> endeavor to <hi>Insinuate</hi> an Ill Opinion of the <hi>Common Prayer,</hi> though you dare not pretend to <hi>Prove</hi> that there is any Passage in it, but what is most Agreeable to the <hi>Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</hi> Unsuitable to the high Subjects, and honorable Work of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Worship! The Lord rebuke you for this that <hi>Diabolical</hi> Calumny of those Forms of Sound Words, in the use of which so many Holy Men in so many Generations have <hi>Offer'd up</hi> their <hi>Hearts,</hi> a <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to the LORD, <hi>Our God.</hi> I have a long time observ'd this subtle <hi>Wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Old Serpent,</hi> viz. that he <hi>Insinuates</hi> into the minds of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny men a most <hi>Injurious</hi> Disesteem of other mens Works, only upon the account of some <hi>Deformity</hi> to their own <hi>Private</hi> Conceits, though it cannot be prov'd that they are any way contrary to the <hi>Rules</hi> of Fit, and Just <hi>&amp;c.</hi> If you would declare what you mean by an <hi>Immethodical Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> I should either Demonstrate that such a Sermon may be better than the best that was ever Preacht by your self, or any one of your Party: Or that our <hi>Liturgy is</hi> altogether unlike to that which you call an <hi>Immethodical Sermon.</hi> If by your <hi>Disorder'd,</hi> and <hi>Defective</hi> you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:66452:4"/> mean that there are any Expressions in the <hi>Liturgy,</hi> in the use of which we may not <hi>Worship</hi> God <hi>in Spirit, and in Truth,</hi> we shall challenge you to shew those Expressions: if your meaning be not this, I shall plainly tell you that you are Guilty of a piece of most <hi>Wicked Sophistry:</hi> And I trust the Lord <hi>Our God</hi> will hear the <hi>Church of</hi> England, Praying <hi>that it may please him to bring into the way of Truth all such as have Erred, and are Deceiv'd</hi> by You, and your <hi>Schismatical</hi> Companions. What prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious <hi>Ignorance</hi> do you discover in your <hi>Cavilling</hi> at the Sign of the Cross? page 178. Here any man may see the most Shameful Effect of your Pride, and Contempt of that Excellent Definition of a <hi>Sacrament</hi> deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd in our <hi>Church-Catechism. The Church Catechism (say you) defineth a Divine Sacrament thus, An outward, and visible sign of an inward, and Spiritual grace given to us, ordained by Christ himself, as a means whereby we receive the same, and a pledge to assure us thereof.</hi> This Definition you most <hi>ridiculously,</hi> or rather most <hi>Lamentably</hi> endeavor to disprove thus: <hi>That it be Ordain'd by Christ himself is not Essential to a Sacrament of Gods making</hi> in Specie, <hi>as distinct from one that's made by Man.</hi> Pray, Sir, consider that you had said, <hi>The Church Catechism desireth a Divine Sacrament thus.</hi> Is it not Essential to a Divine Sacrament that it be Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by Christ himself? And is it not your own Confession that it is a Divine Sacrament which the Catechism desires? God be Prais'd we were never so mad as to Dream of any <hi>Sacrament</hi> but what is Divine (we understand the word <hi>Sacrament</hi> in <hi>sensu Ecclesiastico)</hi> though you are so <hi>Phantastical</hi> as to talk of a Sacrament <hi>that's made by man.</hi> There may be many Outward Visible Signs of an Inward and Spiritual Grace; but that which Constitutes the Nature of a <hi>Sacrament</hi> is this, that it be <hi>Ordain'd by Christ himself, as a means whereby we receive the same (inward, and Spiritual Grace) and a Pledge to assure us thereof.</hi> The Church does not hold that the <hi>Sign of the Cross</hi> is the means of receiving the Grace of God in any other Sense, then as every kind of Profession of Faith in Christ is the Means of Grace, <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>Growing in Grace</hi> &amp;c. Nor does she hold that it was <hi>Ordain'd by Christ himself</hi> in any other sense, then as Every <hi>Lawful,</hi> or <hi>Allowed</hi> Action Perform'd with an <hi>Holy</hi> Intention is Ordain'd by Christ, Our LORD, and <hi>Our God.</hi> So that the Non-conformists may cease from that Fear, which you mention page 180. <hi>The great fear of the Nonconformists is, least this be a second Sacrament of the Covenant of Grace made by man added to Baptism.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I must declare to all the World that the thoughts of this, that I was sign'd with the <hi>Sign of the Cross</hi> immediately after I was <hi>Baptiz'd</hi> have of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten prompted me to such <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Resignation</hi> of my self, and of all my Concerns to the Will of my <hi>Crucified</hi> LORD, that I might <hi>no longer live unto my self but unto him that Dyed for me, and Rose again,</hi> that I cannot but abhorr these Phanatical Wranglings against It, as proceeding from the grand Enemy of the Souls of Men. These words of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are to me <hi>Sweeter than Honey,</hi> and <hi>the Honey-Comb, We receive this Child into the Congregation of Christs Flock and do sign him with the sign of the Cross in token that hereafter he shall not be asham'd to confess the Faith of Christ Crucified, and manfully to fight under his Banner against Sin, the World, and the Devil, and to continue Christs Faithful Soldier, and Servant unto his Lives end.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:66452:5"/>
            <p>The Remembrance of these words Provoke me to Renew my <hi>Vows</hi> to <hi>Fight the good Fight of Faith</hi> hereupon Earth, that I may hereafter <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph</hi> in the Kingdom of Heaven with the <hi>Captain of our Salvation:</hi> By whose Spirit, I say again, and again, I have been often mov'd upon the Remembrance of the <hi>Sign of the Cross</hi> made on my <hi>Fore-head</hi> to cry out with the Apostle: <hi>God forbid that I should Glory, saving</hi> &amp;c. <hi>and the World is Crucifi'd to me.</hi> These Blessed Effects of the Remembrance of being Sign'd with the <hi>Sign of the Cross</hi> which I feel in mine own Soul, have induc'd me to Believe that there are the like in the Souls of Thousands of other Men. We who in our <hi>Preaching,</hi> or <hi>Private Instructions</hi> use this Argument to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade one that is <hi>Baptized</hi> to be <hi>Holy in all manner of Conversation,</hi> that the <hi>Cross</hi> of Christ may be seen on his <hi>Fore-head,</hi> that all men may plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly see that he is <hi>Crucify'd to the World,</hi> that he is such a one, as Our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our speaks of, <hi>Revelations,</hi> 3. 12. <hi>I will write upon him the Name of my GOD, and the Name of the City of my GOD, which is new</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>which cometh down out of Heaven from my GOD:</hi> I say, we Accuse you before the Tribunal of your own Conscience of being highly Guilty of <hi>Disturbing the Peace</hi> betwixt us, and our People in that you endeavor to perswade them to slight that, yea to despise it, and count it a piece of <hi>Superstition,</hi> which we know, and feel, that it may be us'd as a strong Perswasive to the Perfection of Holiness. But here it may be said, is not this an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dervaluing of <hi>Baptism,</hi> to think that a Person <hi>Baptiz'd,</hi> has need of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Minded</hi> of the Sign of the Cross? No surely: For it is nothing else in effect, but to be <hi>Minded</hi> of that most Solemn Acknowledgment made in <hi>Baptism</hi> of our <hi>Obligation to Glory in the</hi> CROSS <hi>of Christ.</hi> Oh, the <hi>Sweetness</hi> that a <hi>sincere</hi> Christian may <hi>Taste</hi> in the sense of these words! In Token that hereafter he shall not be Asham'd to confess the Faith of Christ Crucify'd, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I shall say no more at present but only this, that if you conceit that I shew as much Pride in the severity of the Reproof I have given you, as that, which I charge you withal, I shall entreat you to consider, that if I am Guilty of Pride in this, or in any other Way, our Mother the <hi>Church of England,</hi> calls me to the most effectual Means of being Reclaim'd, in that she commands me to Pray thus with all true Christians: <hi>From all Blindness of Heart, from Pride, Vain Glory and Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie, from Envy, Hatred, and Malice, and all Uncharitableness, Good Lord Deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Farewell, I take my leave of you with this Request, that, to <hi>Calm</hi> your Spirit, you would presently Meditate on these words: Revelation 22. 20. <hi>He which testifieth these things; saith, surely I come quickly.</hi> Amen. <hi>Even so, COME LORD JESUS.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>